A Guide to the Tracy W. McGregor Autograph Collection, ca. 1599-1947
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- SERIES I. LETTERS & MANUSCRIPTS
  - James Madison to James Monroe 1828 Feb 5, ALS, 1p. (Box 5)
    Informs Monroe that he has not heard from Judge Brook and believes that "the task imposed on us by the Convention is of so delicate a nature that with their foreknowledge of our purpose, it ought to have been forborne. Your idea of alluding to the advantage of having the experienced counsel of ex-Presidents in trying contingencies may be more suited to you than to me, more of life being within your prospect than within mine"; #2832
  - James Madison to [Joseph C. Cabell] 1828 Mar 27, ALS, 2p. (Box 5)
    Discusses candidates for the chair vacated by Charles Bonnycastle in Natural Philosophy at the University of Virginia; #4646
  - James Madison to Dr. James Wallace 1828 Jun 24, ALS, 1p. (Box 5)
    Asks him to aid Benjamin Randolph in the procuring of subscriptions to the papers of his grand-father Thomas Jefferson in Fauquier County; #2318
  - James Madison to Mr. Maxwell 1830 Dec 21, ALS, 1p. (Box 5)
    Does not believe that James Sloan's pamphlet on Priestcraft would encounter a favorable reception in his area though Madison has great personal regard for the Revolutionary patriotic zeal of Sloan; #2804
  - James Madison to Stephen Pleasonton n.y. Aug 23, ANS, 1p. (Box 5)
    Does not believe under the circumstances stated in his letter, that James Monroe would disapprove of his trip to [Russia?]; #495
  - Replies to Invitations issued by James Madison, including John Smith of Virginia; Mr. Crawford; Moses Young; E. Campion; G.A. Hughes; General Marton; Thomas Moon; P. Pleasants; N. Pope; Charles Hooks; P. Easton; J. Graham; T. Glendy; N. Glasgow; Isaac Griffin, et als. 1800-1817, 34 ANS (Box 6)
  - Letters & Resolutions concerning the death of James Madison to his wife, Dolley Madison, from Joseph Tate and John H. Pleasants for the citizens of Richmond, Virginia; James Laurie, for the American Colonization Society; and the Henry Literary Society of the Ohio Mechanics Institute; also included is a request from W. McLain that proceeds from a mill and land bequeathed to the American Colonization Society be delivered 1836, 1842, 4 ALS (Box 6)
    #10547-n
  - James Kirke Paulding to Payne Todd 1837 May 24, ALS, 1p. (Box 6)
    Concerning a proposed biography of James Madison; #1562
  - John Marshall to his wife, Mary Marshall 1826 & 1830, 2 ALS (Box 6)
    Discusses his problems with influenza and accompanying symptoms and sticking with his habit of walking three miles by seven (1826); and continues with his morning walk, dinner with President Andrew Jackson and his niece, Mrs. Donelson, of whom Marshall writes, "She is I believe quite popular, but not so popular as Mrs. Madison was." (1830); #5461
  - John Marshall to Major Henry Lee 1830 Oct 25, ALS, 3p. (Box 6)
    Writes in great detail complaining about the representation of the Federalists in the correspondence of Thomas Jefferson recently published by Jefferson's grandson, and discusses his error concerning the French Revolution, Jefferson's aspersions about Marshall himself, Jefferson's political ideas, and ends with, "In truth I have been a skeptic on this subject from the time I became acquainted with Mr. Jefferson as Secretary of State. I have never believed firmly in his infallibility. I have never thought him a particularly wise sound and practical statesman"; #5589
  - Business papers and legal papers of the Marshall family, many in the hand of John Marshall (1755-1835) of Virginia 1763-1829, 38 AD (Box 6)
    Including surveys, reports, petitions, bill of complaints, suits, deeds, bonds, agreements, indentures, and letters concerning legal matters, and involving the following correspondents or participants: Mary Ashby, Edward Carrington, Charles Chinn, Rawleigh Colston, John Conrad, Cornelius Conway, Denny Fairfax, William Fleming, John Gordon, John Halker, Garret Hammersley, Frederick Havely, John Joliffe, Samuel Kercheval, Thomas Lawson, Charles Lee, Daniel Lee, Henry Lee, Peter Lyons, James McCallister, Angus McDonald, Edward McGuire, William McGuire, James Mackie, John Macrae, Charles Marshall, James Marshall, Louis Marshall, Thomas Marshall, William Marshall, Philip Martin, John Milton, John Moffett, John Newman, George Noble, Elizabeth Opie, Thomas Parker, John Peyton, Burr Powell, Edmund Randolph, Joshua Singleton, George Stubblefield, John B. Taylor, Joseph Thompson, James Ware, Lawrence A. Washington, and Elisha Williams; #1106
  - Two Marshall Family Indentures 1789 & 1796, Located in oversize box X-1 (Box 6)
    #1106
  - John Masefield Letters to Mr. [C. F.] Cazenove, Mr. Bornsonn, John Drinkwater, A. Hitchins, and Mr. O'Connor 1906-1913, 5 ALS (Box 6)
    Discussing the terms of an agreement with an agency to collect money due him [Cazenove, 1906 March 12]; thanks for the kind comments and interest in his work [O'Connor, 1907 January 3 and Bornson, 1913 July 11); gives advice on how to develop as a poet [Bornsonn, [1918]]; possible agencies open to Mr. Barker [Drinkwater, [1915] July 30) #10547-o
  - Draft of an Untitled Poem by John Masefield beginning "all the needles clang & clatter" n.d., AMs (Box 6)
    #10547-o
  - George Mason to [Richard Henry Lee ?] 1779 Jun 4, ALS, 4p. (Box 6)
    Writes concerning his problems with gout, the appointment of Thomas Jefferson as governor, the need to restore the state's finances and defending the country, various bills under consideration in the House of Delegates, such as one for moving the seat of government, a tax bill, a resolution ratifying the French alliance, a bill for establishing Boards of Trade and War, a bill for opening a land office, among others, and mentions accounts of a battle with the enemy at Charleston, South Carolina; #990-a
  - George Mason to Arthur Lee 1787 May 21, ALS, 3p. (Box 6)
    Discusses the mission of the delegates meeting in Philadelphia at the U.S. Constitutional Convention, whose most prevalent idea is a total change in the federal system, instituting a great national council upon the principles of equal proportionate representation consisting of two branches of the Legislature, and making the state legislatures subordinate to the national, establishing a national executive, and a judiciary system. He also appends a list of Amendments to the Confederation under consideration. #990-a
  - Two Mather facsimiles, including a letter of dismissal from the Rev. Richard Mather and a memorandum regarding a possessed woman by Cotton Mather, each with transcripts 1660, 1690 (Box 6)
    #38-632
  - Cotton Mather to the Rev. John Cotton 1688 Apr 11, AL, 2p. (Box 6)
    Writes about a friend who is finally able to depart on a vessel after a storm, the malicious designs against his father whose enemies ordered his papers seized and searched wrongfully believing him to be in possession of certain Plymouth papers, his father's plan to journey to England to carry an address of thanks to the king and to restore the charter of Massachusetts, and news garnered from the January gazettes about the pregnancy of the Queen [Mary ?], Pope Innocent XI, Louis XIV, and the Grand Signour; #38-632
  - Cotton Mather to the Rev. James Brown 1690 Apr 30, ALS, 2p. (Box 6)
    Refers to the tribulations and changes brought about in Scotland by the Glorious Revolution, and his father's labor in England on behalf of Massachusetts; #38-632
  - Cotton Mather to the Rev. John Cotton 1690 Oct 17, ALS, 3p. (Box 6)
    Praises his cousin Roland, who accepted a call at Sandwich, discusses Public Occurrences and its printer, Ben Harris, and the untrue rumor that the latest sheet was written by Cotton Mather, and mentions the French despot, Louis XIV, and King William of Orange; #38-632
  - Facsimile copy of Harvard College Testimonial to Dr. Samuel Mather (1677-1746), bearing the earliest Harvard College seal [1701 Jul 3], Facsimile copy (Box 6)
  - Sermon by Cotton Mather preached at Boston 1702 Sep 20, AMs, 8p. (Box 6)
  - List of Marriages performed by Cotton Mather, which also records the birth of his daughter, Elizabeth Mather 1704, AMs, 1p. (Box 6)
    #4860
  - Cotton Mather to the Rev. John Stirling, Vice-Chancellor of the University of Glasgow 1711 Jan 25, ALS, 1p. (Box 6)
    Expresses gratitude for the degree of Doctor of Theology bestowed upon him; #38-632
  - Increase Mather. Notes and scripture references for a sermon "Thanksgiving throughout ye province." 1718 December 2, AD, 1 pp. on one leaf. (Box 6)
    15674
  - Copy of the Will of Increase Mather 1719 Jun 4, AMs, 4p. (Box 6)
  - Cotton Mather to ten ministers re the establishment of the Thursday Lectures in Boston [1720-1?] Jun 22, ALS, 1p. (Box 6)
  - Cotton Mather to [Thomas] Foxcroft 1721 Mar, ALS, 1p. (Box 6)
    Letter of introduction which exhorts Foxcroft to "seize" and convert the bearer of the letter if at all possible; #38-632
  - Receipt to David Edwards signed by Cotton Mather for a legacy from the estate of Mrs. Mary EdwardS 1722 Aug 25, ADS (Box 6)
  - Cotton Mather to Thomas Foxcroft 1722 Aug 26, ALS, 1p. (Box 6)
    Sends a sermon by himself containing a reference to the character of Foxcroft's father-in-law and an unusual metaphor for him to read; #38-632
  - Cotton Mather to Thomas Foxcroft 1722 Aug 28, ALS, 1p. (Box 6)
    Invites Foxcroft to hear him lecture on the coming and Kingdom of God our Savior and the intention of prophecy; #38-632
  - Cotton Mather to Lt. Governor William Dummer 1727 Dec 9, ALS, 3p. (Box 6)
    Mentions a recent earthquake and calls upon the governor to proclaim a general fast and day of humiliation and supplication; #4940
  - "The Pidgeon Py" by Cotton Mather, A Poem in Imitation of A Monumental Gratitude[1727], AMs, 1p., written on back page of a printed copy of that poem (Box 6)
  - Sermon by Samuel Mather on 2 Kings 10:32 1775 Oct 8, AMs (Box 6)
  - Samuel Mather to John Hancock 1776 Sep 18, ALS, 2p. (Box 6)
    Describes Boston under siege, the privations of the people, the wickedness of the British soldiers, favorable comments on the publication of the Declaration of Independence, recommendation that America maintain neutrality in European affairs, credit of the paper bills should be supported, bullion should be acquired and coins stamped; #38-632
  - Sermon by Samuel Mather on Job 23:10 1777 Sep 28, AMs (Box 6)
  - Sermon by Samuel Mather on Psalm 85:8 1782 Mar 28, AMs (Box 6)
  - Sermon by Samuel Mather on Psalm 25:14 1782 Jul 7, AMs (Box 6)
  - Sermon by Samuel Mather on Luke 10:42 1784 Oct 3, AMs (Box 6)
  - Fragment of a Sermon or Essay by Increase Mather n.d., AMs (Box 6)
  - Cotton Mather to "Very dear Sir" n.y. Jun 16, ALS, 1p. (Box 6)
    Discusses his attempts to prevent the spread of rumor and slander about his relationship and conduct with a woman, perhaps the "gentlewoman" whose mystical relation with Mather, terminated by his second marriage, in 1703, caused the Puritan considerable spiritual agitation, together with no inconsiderable scandal in his flock described in his Diary, for February to August 1703; #38-632
  - Cotton Mather to Mrs. [?], a draft of a letter of sympathy and consolation for the death of her son n.d., AL, 2p. (Box 6)
  - Cotton Mather to Thomas Foxcroft Tuesday, ALS, 1p. (Box 6)
    Invitation to preach and mention of "our patriarch" Increase Mather; #38-632
  - Correspondence regarding the engraved portrait of Richard Mather 1917-1918, 8 TLS (Box 6)
  - Sermon by [Cotton Mather] on Psalm 81:16 n.d., AMs (Box 6)
  - Engraving & Prints of Cotton Mather n.d., 8 items (Box 6)
  - Engraving of Increase Mather, purportedly from an original painting in possession of Mr. Townsend, which is believed to be inauthentic. For a full discussion on the merits of this engraving please see The Portraits of Increase Mather, with some notes on Thomas Johnson, an English mezzotinter by Kenneth B. Murdock [1802] (Box 6)
  - Engraving of Increase Mather by I. Sturt n.d. (Box 6)
  - Engravings & Prints of Increase Mather n.d., 9 items (Box 6)
  - Engravings & Prints of Samuel Mather, of Whitney n.d., 4 items (Box 6)
  - News clippings re the Mather family and reviews of Cotton Mather, Keeper of the Puritan Conscience by Ralph and Louise Boas 1920, 1929, Newsprint (Box 6)
  - John Maude to James Breckinridge 1832 Jul 4, ALS, 3p. (Box 6)
    Sends a copy of his book, Visit to the falls of Niagara in 1800, as a token of his appreciation for Breckinridge and his care of his financial interests; compares his work with that of Frances Trollope, commenting on how he drew his impression of the American character from far different Americans than she did her impression; #10547-bz
  - Legal Document, Salem, Massachusetts, concerning the mortgage of Thomas Maule's house and land to Richard Oake, signed by Thomas Maule, John Maule, and Sarah Maule; Thomas Maule was a Salem Quaker 1719 Dec 31 (Box 6)
    #10547-ca
  - Mrs. Elizabeth (Key) Maynadier, sister of John Ross Key, to her sister-in-law, Ann (Charlton) Key, with one letter to Mrs. Roger Brooke Taney 1814, 7 ALS; with typed transcripts (Box 6)
    Discusses events related to the War of 1812, the apprehension of the citizens of Annapolis, British warships on the Chesapeake Bay, plans to move to the safer Belvoir and the "patriotic song" by her nephew, Francis Scott Key; #5107
  - Drafts of Orders from General George Gordon Meade 1863 Oct, 2 ALS (Box 6)
    Concerning the Union army's withdrawal to Rappahannock Station and Centreville during the Bristoe Campaign; #495
  - William Menzies to George Livermore 1861 Sep 30, ALS (Box 6)
    Thanking Livermore for a copy of Soldier's Bible; #10547-cb
  - Letters from Hugh Mercer to Dr. John Morgan and an unidentified correspondent 1767, 1774, 2 ALS (Box 6)
    Writes Morgan concerning a land scheme and readily agrees to participate in corresponding with his medical society; and refers to his correspondent's advertisement to be published in the Pennsylvania and Maryland gazettes and the Governor's decision to decline to grant land warrants to officers out of Virginia; #990
  - Survey of land in Fayette County, Kentucky for James Monroe 1785 Mar 24, AD (Box 7)
    #6089
  - James Monroe to St. George Tucker 1792 Jan 24, ALS, 2p. (Box 7)
    Writes as a U.S. Senator of a discussion in the Senate of the meaning of "The President shall nominate by and with the advice and consent of the Senate appoint" concerning some appointments made by the President for the courts of France, London, and the Hague, especially the appointment of Gouverneur Morris to France, listing his objections to his appointment and his opposition to increasing the size of the standing army to 5,000; #7262
  - James Monroe to Tench Coxe 1792 Apr 13, ALS, 1p. (Box 7)
    Cannot meet with him, being engaged with Mr. Randolph, but does inform him that whatever changes were considered for the Treasury Department have been stricken out, especially concerning the position of assistant secretary; #1661
  - James Monroe to General John Mason 1803 Mar 8, ALS, 1p. (Box 7)
    Writes that it was impossible to make any other financial arrangements to pay Mason than to authorize his agent, Major James Lewis, to sell some property above Charlottesville and a large tract in Kentucky and promises to write him as soon as he reaches France; #1661
  - James Monroe to George Joy 1805 Aug 28, ALS, 1p. (Box 7)
    Mentions the Plate River affair; #2598
  - James Monroe to Sir John Borlase Warren 1813 Apr 16, ALS, 3p. (Box 7)
    Discusses arrangements being made for the speedy exchange of prisoners of war between Great Britain and the United States and the complaints concerning the conduct of the British government towards American seamen; #1661
  - Two page fragment of a draft of comments by James Monroe [1814 Jan], AMs, 2p. (Box 7)
    Concerning the War of 1812, on the effects of two acts just passed by Congress dealing with military organization and pay increases, and an increase in number of men in the military up to 20,000, upon the next campaign; #2315
  - James Monroe to [Charles Everett] 1814 Jun 2, ALS, 3p. (Box 7)
    Advises him to not allow Joseph to publish the book he has in mind and to not consider resignation, as both will render far more damage politically than benefit; #1564
  - James Monroe to Peter Early, Governor of Georgia 1814 Oct 20, ALS, 1p. (Box 7)
    Informs the Governor that the contractor for Georgia is bound to supply rations to the militia as well as the regulars when in service to the United States government; #2288
  - James Monroe to [William Benton] 1818 Aug 14, ALS, 2p. (Box 7)
    Writing from Albemarle County, he discusses the behavior and debts of someone Monroe was responsible for, his wool, his suffering from the heat, an injury to his leg, and asks concerning the progress of the buildings in the capital; #2360
  - James Monroe regarding irregularities in the court martial of Midshipman Campbell and restoration of the man to his duties 1820 Jan 1, ALS, 1p. (Box 7)
    #2360
  - James Monroe to "Dear Sir" 1822 Jul 18, ALS, 1p. (Box 7)
    Refuses to officially sanction a dedication of a book by Sir John Sinclair to himself; #1661
  - Notes on the State of the Union by James Monroe [ca. 1823?], AMs, 1p. (Box 7)
    #2019-a
  - James Monroe to [Albert Gallatin] [ca. 1823?], AN, 1p. (Box 7)
    Asks for a further communication to his government; #3643
  - James Monroe to [Samuel Southard ?] 1825 Aug 16, ALS, 3p. (Box 7)
    Discusses Mrs. Monroe's health, Commodore Porter's conduct in the West Indies, and the Creek Nation's controversy with the state of Georgia; #2474
  - James Monroe to Dr. James Wallace 1828 Dec 15, ALS, 1p. (Box 7)
    Informs the doctor that he has followed his instructions and that his health is improving; #2318
  - James Monroe to Mr. Agg 1829 Nov 3, ALS, 1p. (Box 7)
    Informs Agg that the publication in the Enquirer was slightly altered by Monroe so that he might adopt it for use in The Whig; #1661
  - Daniel Henry Morgan, Prisoner's Camp, Point Lookout, to Anna Morgan 1863 Oct 18, ALS, 1p. (Box 7)
    Informs her that he has received the box with the cake and all his mother's communications, and feels there is little of hope of being exchanged for Yankee prisoners at present; #1275
  - William A. Morgan to his wife, Anna Morgan, writing from Camp Vigilance, Manassas Junction, Fairfax Station, Camp Longstreet, Camp Cooper, and the Headquarters of Rosser's Brigade 1853, 1861-1864, 7 ALS (Box 7)
    Discusses death of George Harris at Camp Vigilance (1861 Jul 12); the first Battle of Manassas (1861 Jul 23); his weariness over the length of the war (1864 Dec 27); #1275
  - Letters to William A. Morgan, including: General Jubal A. Early, Fitzhugh Lee, R.E. Lee, John Letcher, Thomas Munford, George L. Peyton, and Thomas Rosser 1866-1889, 7 ALS (Box 7)
    Concerning business, a Confederate reunion, the exchange of photographs and letters, impression of Minneapolis, Minnesota, the Virginia Hotel, Staunton, Virginia, and an attack on Thomas Rosser by Jubal A. Early in the Richmond "State"; #1275
  - Jedidiah Morse to John Stockdale, London bookseller 1795 Nov 6, ALS, 3p. (Box 7)
    Discusses his gazetteer and other works on geography and refers to critics of Jay's Treaty; #6125
  - John S. Mosby to A.K. McClure 1879 Oct 18, ALS, 2p. (Box 7)
    Writes concerning the embezzlement activities of his predecessor, David H. Baily in the consular service in Hong Kong; #5008
  - John S. Mosby to General J.A. Haldeman 1881 Nov 8, ALS, 1p. (Box 7)
    Thanks him for the basket gift and mentions the possible reconstruction of the Cabinet in Washington, D.C., now that Arthur "the stone that was rejected" has become president, and asks him to convey Washington news; #5008-c
  - John S. Mosby to Jesse C. Green 1888 Sep 25, ALS, 1p. (Box 7)
    Systematically answers the questions in Green's letter about Mosby's Rangers, his relationship with Ulysses S. Grant, Major John Scott's publication Partisan Life with Mosby, and his own book Mosby's Reminiscences; #5008-d
  - John S. Mosby to Robert Maroney 1906 Aug 23, ALS, 1p. (Box 7)
    Writes concerning his war sketches written for the Sunday Magazine and syndicated in The New York Times, which he would like Frank Pemberton to read; #5008-g
  - Letters to John S. Mosby, including: Charles M. Bruce of the Middlesex Club, R. Rathbun, General Frederick W. Grant, Charles F. Winter, Major J.H. Elmsley, Nancy Astor concerning World War I and Great Britain, Thomas P. Bryan, H.C. Stuart, O.W. Beck, H.H. Benedict, Edwin A. Alderman, W. Cameron Forbes, and Walter R. Dorsey 1906-1915, 15 items (Box 7)
    #5008-a,-b
  - John S. Mosby to Major E. Swift 1910 Mar 5, ALS, 1p. (Box 7)
    Asks to borrow his book The Art of Marching for its references to J.E.B. Stuart; #5008-h
  - John S. Mosby to Forest [Beattie] 1910 Dec 6, ALS, 1p. (Box 7)
    Writes concerning his visit at Yale University; #5008-e
  - Robert Morris to Robert James, Agent of the North American Land Company, Instructions of the President & Board of Managers of the North American Land Company for the Superintendence and Management of the Company's Lands in the State of Virginia1796 Jun 1, AMs, 10p. (Box 7)
    #2778
  - John S. Mosby to his grandsons, Mosby and Spottswood Campbell 1903-1916, 70 ALS, 2 folders (Box 7)
    Topics include: encourages grandsons to read Sir Walter Scott's novels with monetary incentives (1903 May 11); has an operation for appendicitis which reminds him of bullet extraction during the war (1908 Jun 1); his visit with the children to the White House where they met Theodore Roosevelt, references to the teddy bear and Edwin A. Alderman raising one million for the University of Virginia (1919 Mar 3); is sending portraits of their parents painted in Paris for his grandsons, and refers to Theodore Roosevelt as a madman following his speech at the Republican Convention (1912 Jun 12); mentions Lady Astor, the "Bull Mooser," and voting for William H. Taft (1912 Oct 25).
    Other topics include: the visit of a lot of suffragettes to Stuart and a mention of Lady Astor (1913 Apr 6); Jack Russell and politics in West Virginia and the Confederate reunion at Gettysburg (1913 May 15); going to the Springs for his health and is writing a book (1913 May 22); his prejudice against post cards (1913 Jun 5); remembers capturing General Wells who will have a statue unveiled at Gettysburg Reunion (1913 Jun 30); mentions the two Battles of Manassas (1914 Jul 9); mentions World War I (1914 Sep 9); Lady Astor (1914 Oct 8); reminiscences about being thrown in the Albemarle County jail when a student at the University of Virginia and expelled from school, a visit from Miss Bettie Page Cocke (1914 Oct 23; 1915 Feb 16).
    He also writes about World War I and its effect on business (1914 Oct 27); comments on Woodrow Wilson (1914 Nov 4); 81st birthday (1914 Dec 6); illness of son Johnnie (1914 Nov 29-Dec 5; 1915 Aug 20-21); visit to the University of Virginia (1915 Feb 16, May 5 & 30); will lecture on Stuart's cavalry at Gettysburg (1915 Mar 4); Cameron Forbes (1915 Mar 4, Sep 12, Oct 23); German naval warfare (1915 Jun 16); death of his son Johnnie (1915 Sep 1 & 8); opposes Woodrow Wilson's "preparedness" (1916 Jan 23, Feb 26); #5008-a,-b, -f
  - Manuscript Note by [Henry Cruse] Murphy (1810-1882) concerning the rarity of Pierre Boucher's history of Canada n.d., ANS (Box 7)
    #10547-cc
  - Thomas Nairne to Charles, Earl of Sunderland 1708 Jul 18, ALS, 5p. (Box 7)